https://mediasmarts.ca/category/categories/privacy

Skip to main content
HomeDigital & Media LiteracyResearchFor ParentsTeacher ResourcesBlogGet Involved
HomeDigital & Media LiteracyGeneral InformationGeneral InformationDigital & Media Literacy FundamentalsInternet & MobileTelevisionMoviesVideo GamesMusicMedia IssuesMedia IssuesBody ImageGender RepresentationDiversity in MediaIntellectual PropertyMarketing & ConsumerismViolenceDigital IssuesDigital IssuesAuthenticating InformationCyberbullyingCyber SecurityExcessive Internet UseGamblingOnline HateOnline EthicsOnline MarketingPrivacyPornographySexual ExploitationSextingEducational GamesEducational Gamese-Tutorials & WorkshopsMedia Literacy WeekResearchFor ParentsTeacher ResourcesFind Lessons & ResourcesFind Lessons & ResourcesDigital and Media Literacy Outcomes by Province & TerritoryMedia Literacy 101Digital Literacy 101Digital Literacy FrameworkClass Tutorials and PD Workshops (Licensed)Class Tutorials and PD Workshops (Licensed)My Licensed ResourcesBlogGet InvolvedMedia Literacy WeekBecome a donorBecome a sponsorBecome a volunteer
Privacy
Young Canadians Speak Out: A Qualitative Research Report on Privacy and ConsentSubmitted by MediaSmarts on 31 Mar 2020.
Informed Youth Promote Clarity for All
It’s something we’ve all done before: scrolled past a wall of text to click “I Agree” with no idea what we’ve agreed to. Then, when we’re using the platform, messages like “We’ve made some changes to our Terms and Conditions” simply remind us that we probably didn’t read them in the first place. Our world is becoming more and more influenced by the data that’s being collected about us. For young people in particular, this can lead to serious and unexpected consequences that could affect their entire lives.Read moreAdd a Comment (0 submitted)
Internet & Mobile,
Privacy
Keeping up with kids in a wireless worldSubmitted by MediaSmarts on 09 Mar 2020.
By Samantha McAleese, research associate at MediaSmarts and
David Fowler, vice-president, marketing and communications at CIRA.Read moreAdd a Comment (0 submitted)
Digital Health,
Internet & Mobile,
Parents,
Privacy,
Social Networking
Getting paranoid about our smart speakerSubmitted by Lynn Jatania on 27 Nov 2019.
The other day I was on the phone with my sister – our land line, not a cell phone – and I said to her, “You’re my person.” This is a well-known phrase from the TV show Grey’s Anatomy; Meredith Grey and Cristina Yang used to say it to each other to cement the closeness of their friendship.Read moreAdd a Comment (0 submitted)
Cyber Security,
Internet & Mobile,
Parents,
Privacy
In this lesson, students examine a fictional social network profile to learn how online platforms collect data about their users. They then read an article that explains how platforms use this data and explores some of the issues this raises. Finally, they create a mind map of their own online data profile and reflect on how the data they post may be collected and used by others.
Language
English
Read more about The Invisible Machine: Big Data and You
Drawing the Privacy LineSubmitted by Lynn Jatania on 14 Jun 2019.
I read an interesting Facebook post the other day, written by a teenaged girl. She said quite firmly that it was important for parents to not have their children’s passwords, for their phone or social media accounts. She talked about building trust and how insisting on knowing your kids’ passwords is the first step to them sneaking around online and getting involved in things you wish they wouldn’t.
Read moreAdd a Comment (0 submitted)
Cell Phones and Texting,
Parents,
Privacy
An Incident at SchoolSubmitted by Lynn Jatania on 24 May 2019.
I admit I was hoping to never get an email like this from the school:
“Some students in your child’s class have been involved in inappropriate online behaviour. Our Student Resource Officer will be doing a presentation on cyberbullying and leading a discussion about responsible actions on the internet. Please speak to your child about his/her activity online.”
Read moreAdd a Comment (0 submitted)
Cell Phones and Texting,
Parents,
Privacy
Keeping It Private OnlineSubmitted by Lynn Jatania on 11 Feb 2019.
Recently, my nephew, age 12, received a letter in the mail. It was addressed to him personally, by name. Inside was a photocopied article about the powers of a new virility medicine, complete with the usual graphic promises for pleasuring the ladies. The article mentioned a specific “doctor” by name, but other than that, there was no contact information or order form or any other action request. It appeared to just be spam but in paper form.
Read moreAdd a Comment (0 submitted)
Cell Phones and Texting,
Cyber Security,
Internet & Mobile,
Parents,
Privacy
Knowing My PasswordSubmitted by Lynn Jatania on 10 Dec 2018.
My three kids all know the password to my phone.
It’s because I rely on them to play secretary for me when I’m driving. If the phone rings or there is a bing of a text, 99% of the time it’s a member of my immediate family trying to get in touch with something relatively pressing.
Read moreAdd a Comment (0 submitted)
Cell Phones and Texting,
Cyber Security,
Parents,
Privacy
In this lesson, students are introduced to the privacy principles that inform the Alberta and BC Personal Information Protection Acts, Québec’s An Act Respecting the Protection of Personal Information in the Private Sector and the students’ federal Personal Information Protection and Electronic Documents Act (PIPEDA) relating to personal information collection online. They learn ways to find out what personal information may or has been collected by platforms that they use, how to limit data collection about themselves, and the various forms of recourse that are available to them if they feel an organization is not respecting their rights.
Language
English
Read more about Privacy Rights of Children and Teens
In this lesson, students are introduced to the idea that privacy is a fundamental human right and that their personal information is valuable. The lesson focuses on the “economics” of personal information and that most “free” apps and online services make some or all of their revenue by collecting (and in some cases reselling) users’ personal information. Students will watch a video that illustrates the idea that they may be paying with their privacy and then discuss some of the ramifications of this. They will learn about tools and techniques for minimizing the personal information they share and create a public service announcement that helps them and their peers “know the deal” about the value of privacy.
Language
English
Read more about Know the Deal: The Value of Privacy
Pages12345678next ›last »
Sign up
Stay informed with daily news and updates!
Learn more
How to Support Us
Interested in supporting MediaSmarts? Find out how you can get involved.
Charitable Registration No. 89018 1092 RR0001
Learn more
Follow Us
Stay connected with us on social media
General InformationDigital & Media Literacy FundamentalsInternet & MobileTelevisionMoviesVideo GamesMusic
Media IssuesBody ImageGender RepresentationDiversity in MediaIntellectual PropertyMarketing & ConsumerismViolence
Digital IssuesAuthenticating InformationCyberbullyingCyber SecurityExcessive Internet UseGamblingOnline HateOnline EthicsOnline MarketingPrivacyPornographySexual ExploitationSexting
Educational Gamese-Tutorials & WorkshopsMedia Literacy Week
Find Lessons & ResourcesDigital and Media Literacy Outcomes by Province & TerritoryMedia Literacy 101Digital Literacy 101Digital Literacy Framework
Class Tutorials and PD Workshops (Licensed)My Licensed Resources
Media Literacy WeekBecome a donorBecome a sponsorBecome a volunteer
